Nikita Lazarev | CV

Aurora Street – Ithaca – NY, USA > 16073790757 • > 1524@cornell.edu

Research Interests

Computer Hardware: Networking Hardware, SmartNICs, FPGAs, System Interconnects **Computer Systems:** Networking and Distributed Systems, Kernel Bypass Technologies **Application Domains:** Low-Latency Systems, Datacenter Systems, 5G and vRAN

Current Research Focus: (1) Pushing further and making practical the tight integration of datacenter machines via closely-coupled with processors FPGAs; (2) Making 5G vRAN stacks as a cloud native feature by leveraging advances in low-latency networking and realtime distributed systems.

Education

Cornell University Ithaca, NY, USA

Computer Engineering: PhD 2019–

Swiss Federal Institute of Technology (EPFL)

Lausanne, Switzerland

Computer Science: MS 2016–2018

Bauman Moscow State Technical University

Moscow, Russia

Electrical Engineering & Robotics: Engineer 2010–2016

Research Experience

Industry....

Microsoft Azure for Operators Research (part-time researcher) Redmond, WA, USA

Layer disaggregation and workload migration in 5G/vRAN stacks

06.2021 - now

Research and development towards enabling MAC/PHY layer disaggregation and 5G workload migration in the future Azure vRAN infrastructure. I developed a DPDK-based component for the layer disaggregation, and implemented and tested cell migration logic in FlexRAN, both in local and distributed settings under the real 5G workload.

Microsoft Research, Systems and Networking lab (internship) Cambridge, UK

FPGA-based implementation of a transport network layer for the specific workload 06.2018 - 09.2018

Fork of the Microsoft FaRM project. The goal is to design a CPU-free datastore architecture for the applications in distributed graph databases and key-value stores. Such applications cause intense network traffic composed of small randomly addressed packets, and my task was to design the transport layer adopted for such workload. As the result, the network performance was improved by 30% in comparison with the previously used transport layer.

Microsoft Research, Systems lab (internship)

Bangalore, India

Hardware acceleration of real-time IoT AI algorithms

08.2017 - 02.2018

Two ML algorithms have been optimized at MSRI in order to fit on resource-constrained IoT devices. In this project, I was working on a design of an FPGA-based heterogeneous SoC for efficient implementation of those optimized algorithms in hardware. The designed SoC enables low-latency implementation of the algorithms, and it is generic: both algorithms can be implemented leveraging exposed SW interfaces without changing the hardware.

Samsung Research Center (part-time)

Moscow, Russia

Junior software developer: compiler technologies and systems

2014 - 2016

Android ART compiler and runtime optimization. Focus on compiler optimization: loop transformations, division optimization, heterogeneous back-end support. Focus on runtime optimization: hash tables for Java strings. Research focus: speed-up of class loading by static analysis of the class references.

Academia.....

Cornell University Ithaca, NY, USA

Independent research, supervisor: Prof. Zhiru Zhang, Prof. Christina Delimitrou 02.2020 -FPGAs in datacenters: exploring the opportunities of closely-coupled FPGAs for improving networking performance

and acceleration of datacenter tax functions.

Swiss Federal Institute of Technology (EPFL) Lausanne. Switzerland 02.2018 - 07.2018

Term project, supervisor: Prof. Babak Falsafi

Development of a lightweight VLIW-like SIMD core for a neural processor

Lausanne. Switzerland Swiss Federal Institute of Technology (EPFL)

Research assistantship: setup of a quantum mechanics experiment 02.2017 - 07.2017

Development and production of a fast FPGA-based PID control system for lasers

Bauman Moscow State Technical University Moscow, Russia

2013 - 2014 Term project

Phasechronometric measurement device: FPGA programming and PCB design

Lomonosov Moscow State University Moscow, Russia

2012 - 2013 Independent project

Brain - computer interface: RF-PCB design, microcontroller firmware development, deep learning

Teaching Experience

Cornell University Ithaca, NY, USA

Digital logic and computer organization (ECE-2300): teaching assistant 2021

Keywords: computer architecture, FPGA, Verilog

EPFL Lausanne, Switzerland

Real-time embedded systems (CS-476): teaching assistant 2018

Keywords: FPGA, hardware accelerator, VHDL

Microsoft Research Bangalore, India

Tutorial: introduction to FPGAs 2017

Keywords: FPGA, hardware accelerator

Bauman Moscow State Technical University Moscow, Russia

Implementation of control systems: guest lecturer 2015

Keywords: control systems, PID, microcontrollers

Key implementation skills

Software skills.....

Top programming languages: C++, Python, C, Scala, Java

Domains: Kernel bypass networking, distributed systems, vRAN and 5G, realtime and embedded systems, machine learning, compiler optimization and runtime systems

Hardware skills.....

RTL languages: System Verilog, VHDL, Chisel

HLS languages: SystemC

Domains: SmartNICs and networking devices, AI accelerators

Key research/theoretical skills

Theory of algorithms, distributed systems, computer systems, machine learning, probability and statistics, complexity theory, basics of signal processing and control, basics of game theory

Languages

Russian: Mother tongue

English: Fluent French: Elementary

Selected Publications

A Roadmap for Enabling a Future-Proof In-Network Computing Data Plane Ecosystem
 D. Kim, N. Lazarev, T. Tracy, F. Siddique, H. Namkung, J. Hoe, V. Sekar, K. Skadron, Z. Zhang, S. Seshan

Arxiv pre-print, October, 2021

 Dagger: Efficient and Fast RPCs in Cloud Mcroservices with Near-Memory Reconfigurable NICs

Nikita Lazarev, Neil Adit, Shaojie Xiang, Zhiru Zhang, Christina Delimitrou ASPLOS'21, April, 2021

 Dagger: Towards Efficient RPCs in Cloud Microservices with Near-Memory Reconfigurable NICs

Nikita Lazarev, Neil Adit, Shaojie Xiang, Zhiru Zhang, Christina Delimitrou IEEE Computer Architecture Letters, August, 2020

Patents

Precise FPGA-based time measurement system for real-time turning process monitoring
 A. Syritsky, D. Boldasov, N. Lazarev, A. Komshin
 Registration number: RU2019610688

Achievements

- Cornell University graduate research fellowship
- Samsung Research "Above and Beyond" award
- Presidential Scholarship award
- Best inventive project award on the All Russian Technical Exhibition of Student Projects "Polytechnika"
- o 3rd place on the Russian competition of IT projects "IT breakthroughs"
- Medal for excellent graduation (Bauman Moscow State Technical University)
- o 2nd place on the national Olympiad for Physics and Mathematics, Olympiad level II
- o 1st place on the regional competition of programming projects for high school students